In this demo, we'll be creating a program that utilizes ranges.
Once you're ready, fire up Visual Studio Code, and let's go.
Once Visual Studio Code loads navigate to the demo folder.
We are on the ranges demo, so click on the ranges folder,
and then double click on ranges.go.
So when we use the range keyword, it's going to automatically
create an iterator for us.
And so it's kind of like an easier way of making a for loop with the counter.
So let's start by making a slice.
So like a string slice.
We'll have a low world and an exclamation point.
So we'll have four I comma element.
Sign equals range slice.
So when we use range, we're going to get two things back from this slice.
I will be the index number.
And element will be the thing in the slice.
So it's always going to start at zero for I.
And then elements in this case will be hello.
And then the second iteration will be world.
And then the third will be the exclamation point.
So we'll have a we'll do a print line that we can see what gets printed out.
So we'll print I and elements.
Let's just run that as is and then we'll add some more to it.
So I'll hop into a terminal.
You can run this with go run dot slash demo slash ranges.
And so here we have the zero hello one world to exclamation point.
So now we that we have the range keyword.
We're going to be able to iterate over individual letters of these strings.
If you'll recall from our previous lecture,
I did mention that we're not able to go through letters by using a typical for loop.
So if we had a loop like this and we hit something like that.
And try to go into the slice.
Like that to access the letters of hello.
This isn't going to work because we're going through individual bytes of that string.
And if you'll recall, the letters take up more than one byte in some cases,
like special characters or emoji for example.
So we're not able to do this to access each letter.
However, when we use the range keyword,
it's going to automatically account for all that for us.
And so we are able to go through each letter when we have the range keyword.
So let me delete this.
And now we'll go through each letter.
So I'm going to ignore the index for this case.
And I'll just use CH and CH will just be short for our character.
I'll go from a range of elements.
So this outer loop here is going to go through each one of these words.
And this inner loop is going to go through each letter of each word.
I'll do a print F in this case.
A little bit of spaces.
And if we do percent to Q, we'll actually print out the glyph representation of these runes.
Because each one of these is a rune.
I'm also going to add a little bit here.
So now thanks to range, we get the length.
The first range here, we're getting the length of the string automatically for us
because we don't have to check to see how far long we are in the iteration.
And on the second range, we're getting the same thing.
We're getting the length of the total number of characters in these strings, not the bytes.
So we're going to get individual letters regardless of how many bytes they consume
and how complex they are.
And when we use percent Q within this print F function,
we're able to print out a rune instead of just the number of the rune.
So let's hop back into a terminal and see what happens.
And so on our first iteration, we print out hello.
And then each iteration of the inner loop, we have each letter being printed out.
And the same thing for world and the same thing for the exclamation.
This is just a short demo on the range keyword.
It's pretty straightforward.
And for the most part, simulates the typical for loop with the iteration and the counter.
Except it also takes into account the glyph representation of these string and runes.
We're also able to use a range on different data types that will be covering later on in the course.
And finally, one of the most convenient thing about ranges is we don't have to calculate the length or anything,
because all of that is considered within the range keyword itself.
And it's totally normal to ignore either the index or the element depending on what you're trying to do.
Let's conclude the demo on the range keyword.
I'll see you in the next presentation.